<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;वेङ्कटरमणः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/rUpakam/venkaTaramaNaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;वेङ्कटरमणः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/rUpakam/venkaTaramaNaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>कमलाविजयनाटकम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/rUpakam/venkaTaramaNaH/kamalAvijayanATakam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/rUpakam/venkaTaramaNaH/kamalAvijayanATakam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[कमलाविजयनाटकम्&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=ODMwOTAxMDA2MzYxMTI1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opinion by Dr. Ganganatha Jha, &lt;em&gt;Ex&lt;/em&gt;-Vice-Chancellor of&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Allahabad University.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have had the pleasure of meeting Pandit C. Venkataramanaiya of Bangalore, and listening to his poems. It is a great consolation to find among us such writers of Sanskrit. His poems bear true mark of the true poet, and bear testimony to his wonderful command over the language, and its niceties. I hope he will find a publisher for his works. Works like his deserve to live; it would be a pity if they are lost for want of publicity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>जीवसञ्जीविनीनाटकम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/rUpakam/venkaTaramaNaH/jIvasanjIvinInATakam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/rUpakam/venkaTaramaNaH/jIvasanjIvinInATakam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[जीवसञ्जीविनीनाटकम्&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=NjA1NDU2MjI2Nzg1MDI1&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;प्रकटनम्&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;एतद्ग्रन्थसम्बन्धाधिकारः कोऽपि ग्रन्थकर्त्रा न स्वायत्तीकृतः। तस्माद्यदा कदावाप्यधिकानि पुस्तकान्यपेक्षितानि भवन्ति, तदा यस्य कस्य वा एतद्ग्रन्थस्य पुनर्मुद्रणकार्ये भवति निरर्गलोऽधिकारः। परन्तु ग्रन्थस्य स्वायत्तीकरणे न तस्याधिकारः। तथाप्ययं ग्रन्थः व्याख्यान्तरसमेतो वा, विवरणसहकृतो वा भाषान्तरपरिवर्तनपरिष्कृतो वा यदि भवेत् तदा तद्व्याख्यादिकर्तुः तत्प्रतिनिधेः, विश्वविद्यापीठादेः, तादृशव्याख्याद्युपेतस्यास्य ग्रन्थस्य न्यायतः स्वायत्तीकरणपूर्वकमेवसर्वे मुद्रणाद्यधिकाराः निश्चिताः, ग्रन्थकर्तृसम्मताश्च भवन्ति॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;बेङ्गलूरु,                         &lt;br&gt;&#xA;श्रीवेङ्कटरमणार्यः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;२५-२-१९४५                            &lt;br&gt;&#xA;ग्रन्थकर्ता&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Announcement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Copyright of this work is not reserved by the author, as the work is solely intended for the general enlightenment. So, if more copies are required at any time, any individual or agency may get the work reprinted in any number of copies, without claiming copyright for the work. If, however, any explanations or notes, or translation in any language is written on, and affixed to the work, then copyright may, justly and rightly, be claimed and reserved by any individual or his agent or representative or by Educational Institution, or by any other agency.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
