<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;तिरुवेङ्कटाचार्य-प्रस्तावः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;तिरुवेङ्कटाचार्य-प्रस्तावः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Historical value</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/historical-value/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/historical-value/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is an irony that the country with the most ancient civilization should have very few original histories about its past. Strictly speaking, the only historical work of the past worth the name of history is Kalhana&amp;rsquo;s Rājatarangini, which tells the story of the kings of Kashmir. Bana&amp;rsquo;s Harshacaritam is no doubt very valuable as a biography but there is a great deal in it that does not partake of the nature of correct history. It is only when we reach what is often called the Muslim period of Indian History that we have regular histories, whatever may be the degree of their objectivity. Because of this paucity of historical works belonging to the earlier periods western scholars have sometimes criticised Indians as lacking any historical sense. But there is a great deal in our ancient literature which we can press into service in the writing of Indian history. It will be profitable to read the Foreword to the first volume of the Indian History series published by The Bharatiya Itihasa Samiti in which Mr. K. M. Munshi has discussed the scope and limitations of our literary sources in the reconstruction of India&amp;rsquo;s past history.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Madurai conquest</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/madurai-conquest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/madurai-conquest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-the-political-condition-preceding-the-conquest&#34;&gt;1. THE POLITICAL CONDITION PRECEDING THE CONQUEST&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Among the territories that suffered the worst rapine and plunder was Ma&amp;rsquo;bar. According to Khusrau’ Ma’bar lay within that distance from Delhi which could be reached after a normal journey of twelve months. As Khusrau says, the Muslim arrows had never reached that distant land”. As regards the identity of ĪMa’bar there is no doubt. The region of the Coromandal east of Peninsular India might be said to correspond roughly to what was known to Arab geographers as Ma&amp;rsquo;bar. The author of Taquivim ul-Buldān quoted by Al-Qalquashandi (Subh ul-A-sha) (Ed. by Otto Spies) says that Ma&amp;rsquo;bar &amp;ldquo;lies to the east of Kaulam (possibly Kollam or Quilon at three or four days journey in a southerly direction”). Ibn Sa&amp;rsquo;ib quoted by the same source says, “it is well-known and muslin is exported from there; its washermen are proverbial&amp;rdquo; What was the condition of Ma&amp;rsquo;bar at that time ?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preface</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/preface/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Madhurāvijayam or Vīra Kamparāya caritam by Gangā Dēvi was discovered by accident amidst a heap of worn out palm-leaf manuscripts as part of a series of Sanskrit works; and, but for the careful scrutiny of the Head Pandit of the curator of Sanskrit Mss. Trivandrum, it would have gone the way of many other works of the past which are not available to us. The original is in grantha characters and is full of errors. The manuscript, as discovered, was incomplete, with ten leaves missing in the middle and many slokas incomplete in the available portion. Though it is not possible to say how many slokas have been lost, it is fairly certain that the complete work might have included at least seventy more verses than are extant now.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SAMBUVARĀYAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/sAmbuvarAyas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/sAmbuvarAyas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;II. THE SAMBUVARĀYAS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-vīra-champa&#34;&gt;1. VĪRA CHAMPA&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Madhurāvijayam, as its title signifies, is the story of the conquest of Madhurai by Kumāra Kampaņa told by his wife Gangā Dēvi. But the poem treats also of the factors which formed the prelude to the Madhurai conquest. The way to Madhurai lay through the Tondai mandalam which was at that time ruled by the Sambuva rāyas. It is not certain whether the Sambuvarāya kings were on friendly terms with the new kingdom of Vijayanagar. Apart from the political ambition to add terri tories to the kingdom, there was always the danger of the Muslims overrunning the whole of the Tamil country and proving a serious menace to Vijayanagar. Therefore, there was the need to clear the Tamil country of all forces detrimental to the existence and expansion of Vijayanagar. The Sambuvarāyas cccupied a strategic position in the Tamil country between Vijaya nagar and the Madhurai Sultanate. They should either be reduced to the position of feudatories to Vijayanagar or destroyed. Bukka placed emphasis on the need to remove all the political cobwebs before launching the attack on Madhurai. So the Sambuvarāyas were the first enemies of Vijayanagar that had to be tackled by Kampana. A brief account of the Sambuvaraya rule in the Tondaimandalam region will be of interest to students of early Vijayanagar history.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The poet</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/poet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/poet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The peculiar interest of this biographical poem is that its author Gangā Dēvi was the wife of the hero whom it celebrates, and that in all probability she accompanied her husband in his sojourns in the South. She was the chief queen of Kampaņa II, and though nothing is known about her lineage, must have sprung from a noble family as the Dēvi suffix would imply. She was very highly accomplished and was endowed with all charms and grace. Kampaņa lavished all his love and attention on her though he had other wives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Viajayanagara invasions of Tondaimandalam</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/vijayanagara-invasions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/gangAdevI_madhurA-vijayam/meta/00_tiruvenkaTAchAri/vijayanagara-invasions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;IV. VIJAYANAGAR INVASIONS OF TONDAIMANDALAM&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-the-savanna-interregnum&#34;&gt;1. THE SAVANNA INTERREGNUM&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is believed by some scholars that it was Venrumankondān I the Sambuvarāya ruler (1322 1339) who was overcome by Kampana. But this view is far from correct as the earliest inscription of Kampana bears only the date 1352.2 His invasion of Tondai mandalam could never have taken place prior to that year. Venrumaņkondān had a peaceful death and the period was also calm and quiet in his territory, and this is borne out by the fact that his son Kājanārāyana was able to send the remains of his royal father to be consigned to the Ganges..&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
