<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;ति।वि।कपालिशास्त्री on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/prakIrNam_kAvyam/padyam/stotrANi/ti.vi.kapAlishAstrI/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;ति।वि।कपालिशास्त्री on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/prakIrNam_kAvyam/padyam/stotrANi/ti.vi.kapAlishAstrI/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>भारतीस्तवः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/prakIrNam_kAvyam/padyam/stotrANi/ti.vi.kapAlishAstrI/bhAratIstavaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/prakIrNam_kAvyam/padyam/stotrANi/ti.vi.kapAlishAstrI/bhAratIstavaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[भारतीस्तवः&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=Njc0NDEwOTc0MTQ1Nzc2&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PUBLISHER&amp;rsquo;S NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;BHARATI-STAVA is an outstanding poem of Sri T.V. Kapali Sastry. Sung on the eve of the Independence of India—15th of August 1947—this Song of the Soul of Indiain a century of verses, rolls into seven distinct spheres onseven metrical modes. The poet greets the New Age thatis dawning after India&amp;rsquo;s lot of severe stress and suffering,invokes the Name of Sri Aurobindo, the Prophet of India&amp;rsquo;sindependence who first saw in his vision the advent of her freedom and the high mission she was destined tofulfil. The main theme is indeed the Soul of India, butwith all her features whose moulds are to be seen in thepageant of her march at the head of nations in Arts, Craftsand Sciences, and not merely in things of the Spirit. Theirstamp is indelible and could be seen in the richness of theirdiverse forms in the field of action and thought, in religionsand philosophies in which even Nihilism of a sort found a place. It takes in a sweep a summary, yet comprehensive, view of the distinctive catholicity of her Dharma, themeaning of the appearance of Rama, Krishna and otherworld-moving Figures on her soil. Lastly, the voice ofreasoning appeal, supplication and worship rises andgoes forth to Mother India who is addressed as &lt;em&gt;Bhārati&lt;/em&gt;following the ancient tradition:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
