<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;हर्षकीर्तिः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/harShakIrtiH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;हर्षकीर्तिः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/harShakIrtiH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>शारदीयाख्यनाममाला</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/harShakIrtiH/shAradIyAkhyanAmamAlA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/harShakIrtiH/shAradIyAkhyanAmamAlA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[शारदीयाख्यनाममाला&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=MjQ0MjIyNjE1MjI0NTU4&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;———————————————————————————————————————————&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Printed by S. R. Sardesai, B.A., LL.B., at the Navin Samarth Vidyalaya’s&lt;br&gt;&#xA;‘Samarth Bharat Press’, 41 Budhwar Peth, Poona 2, and Published&lt;br&gt;&#xA;by Dr. S. M. Katre, for the Deccan College Post-graduate&lt;br&gt;&#xA;and Research Institute, Yeravda, Poona 6,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**PREFACE **&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It gives me great pleasure to present to the world of scholars the present edition of the ŚŚ&lt;em&gt;āradīyākhyanāmamālā&lt;/em&gt; of Harṣakīrti shortly after my edition of the &lt;em&gt;Anekārthatilaka&lt;/em&gt; of Mahīpa published in the same Series in 1947. The work of preparing a critical edition of the &lt;em&gt;Śāradīyākhyanāmamālā&lt;/em&gt; was entrusted to me in the year 1950 by Dr. S. M. KATRE, Director of the Deccan College Research Institute, Poona, for being included in the Institute’s Series called the ‘Contributory Studies towards A Dictionary of Sanskrit on Historical Principles’ in general and the ‘Sources of Indo-Aryan Lexicography’ in particular. I started my work on the critical edition of the ŚN soon after it was entrusted to me by procuring five manuscripts of the work-four from the Government Manuscripts Library at the Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute, Poona and one from the Manuscripts Library of the Deccan College Research Institute and having worked at it at different intervals, submitted to the Institute my press-copy early in January 1951. I am glad that the work is now available in print without any delay.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
