<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अधिपुराणम् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अधिपुराणम् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Arjun - booklist</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/arjun_booklist/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/arjun_booklist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.prekshaa.in/article/pur%C4%81%E1%B9%87a-booklist&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The _Purāṇa_s occupy a high rank amongst India’s literary contribution to the world. In addition to being written lore of the highest magnitude, the _Purāṇa_s have also remained in the oral tradition, percolating to the grassroots. They eminently represent the very nature of &lt;em&gt;Sanātana-dharma&lt;/em&gt; and can easily qualify as ‘the encyclopaedia of the commoners.’ While the _Veda_s express the aspirations, inspirations, amazement, and philosophy of the ancient _ṛṣi_s, the _Purāṇa_s make the _Veda_s accessible to the masses in an engaging manner.&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftn1&#34;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; Kṛṣṇa-dvaipāyana, the &lt;em&gt;ṛṣi&lt;/em&gt; who reorganised the _Veda_s into four and thus gained the epithet ‘Veda-vyāsa’ is said to have authored all the _Purāṇa_s for the welfare of the world.&lt;a href=&#34;#_ftn2&#34;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; The etymology of the word ‘&lt;em&gt;purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;’ reveals a lot about its content – पुरापि नवं इति पुराणम् – &lt;em&gt;although ancient, it is eternally new and always relevant&lt;/em&gt;. The stories, ideas, and philosophy contained in the _Purāṇa_s are ancient, but their value is timeless, and hence, relevant to all times. The _Purāṇa_s can be compared to the river Gaṅgā. The divine river has been flowing in the heartland of India for millions of years; yet, at every moment and at every point in its flow, the water is fresh – the waters of Gaṅgā are important and relevant to us, at all times. Though ancient, the Gaṅgā is perennial, eternal, enriching and life-sustaining. Such is the nature of the _Purāṇa_s.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>purANa-philosophy-eminence</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/purANa-philosophy-eminence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/purANa-philosophy-eminence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.prekshaa.in/archive?field_author_article_target_id=9767&#34;&gt;prekshaa series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[[The Eminence and the Philosophy of Puranas&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.prekshaa.in/article/eminence-and-philosophy-puranas&#34;&gt;prekshaa&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: This is the first part of a series of the English translation of Mahamahopadhyaya Vidwan Sri N. Ranganatha Sarma’s Kannada monograph titled, &lt;em&gt;purāṇagaḻa nele mattu tattvavicāra&lt;/em&gt; published in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;preface&#34;&gt;Preface&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the expansive accomplishments of Indians in the field of literature, historical works (&lt;em&gt;itihāsa&lt;/em&gt;) like the Vedas, Upanishads, Srimad Ramayana, and Mahabharata, and Puranic works like skāndapurāṇa, viṣṇupurāṇa and others are world-renowned works that bring pride to any country. The various stories, wise sayings, and more importantly, philosophical elements that are related to the &lt;em&gt;Atman,&lt;/em&gt; are contemplative topics that attract scholars. From the ancient times, our people have called the Ramayana and Mahabharata as works of &lt;em&gt;itihāsa&lt;/em&gt; or history. Therefore, we must consider Sri Rama, Lakshmana, Bhishma, Drona and others as real people who lived at some point in history, i.e., they were historical persons. Because they are an inextricable part of our mahākāvya-s (great literature), the supernatural and magical descriptions woven around them by the poet is entirely appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
