<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;क्षमाराव् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/xamArAv/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;क्षमाराव् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/xamArAv/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>उत्तरसत्याग्रहगीता</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/xamArAv/uttarasatyAgrahagItA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/aitihyam/kAvyam/padyam/xamArAv/uttarasatyAgrahagItA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[उत्तरसत्याग्रहगीता&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=NjU1MjQ3MTM4Mjg5MjQ2&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOREWORD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;** **In Sanskrit more than in any other language women poets have at all times been held in high honour. Apart from quotations in well-known anthologies many notable works by women poets of earlier times have come down to us. Among them may be mentioned the well-known political drama *Kaumudi Mahotsava,*Queen Ganga Devi&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Kavya&lt;/em&gt; entitled &lt;em&gt;Madhura Vijaya&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;Champu Varadambika Parinaya&lt;/em&gt;. Pandita Ksama Row, who is undoubtedly our most eminent Sanskrit poetess, is therefore the inheritor of a great tradition which she has upheld and enriched with great distinction. Her earlier publications, especially &lt;em&gt;Katha Panchakam&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mīra Lahrī,&lt;/em&gt; have earned for her an honoured place not only among poets writing in Sanskrit, but in the modern Indian literary world. The &lt;em&gt;Purva&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Satyagraha Gita&lt;/em&gt; brought her deserved fame as an epic poet, for in that volume she had, in the manner of Valmiki and Vyas, dealt with the story of Gandhiji&amp;rsquo;s life up to the Gandhi-Irwin Pact. The present volume is the second part of that epic, bringing the story of the great struggle to the 75th birth-day of Gandhiji.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
