<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०३ NOTES on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०३ NOTES on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>०१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;कुमारसंभवम् - कुमारस्य संभव: the birth of Kumara or Kártikeya ; स एवाभेदोपचारात् कुमारसंभवं काव्यं, the same denotes the composition descriptive of it by &amp;rsquo;the transference of an epithet.” Cf. (gin, zandi &amp;amp;c,; sec Sid. Kau, ou Pán. IV. 3. 87.&#xA;(Sl.) 1. sfeer &amp;amp;c.—A poet may introduce a poem by invoking a blessing (3⁄41⁄2ff:) on his readers or the audience, or by a salutation ( 7¤ímur ) to his favourite deity, or by indicating the subject (ajaïa ) at once, as horo. See Malli. The letter अ as representing Vishnu ( अकारो विष्णुरुद्दिष्टः see our note on ч017 Rag. I, 11) is auspicious (Mangalika). gateri içinThat is the region to the north of Central India or #suŻN, which is considered holy. area—having a divine being for its presiding or animating deity ( i, e. who is a deity himself ) and so having another and a divine form as distinguished from the Sthápara form. The purpose served by this epithet is explained by Malli. (gäareg&amp;hellip;: i. . capacity to discharge tho functions of a living being ). हिमालय: - हिमवान्हेमकुदश्व निषधस्तस्य दक्षिणे । नीलश्वेतश्व सृङ्गी च उत्तर वर्षपर्वताः ॥ V. P. One Commentator strangely derives this as हि निश्वितं स्फुटं मा लक्ष्मीस्तस्या आलयः । अधिराज : &amp;ndash;&amp;amp; Pradi. Tat comp. अधिरैश्वर्ये अधिकस्य राजा; Char. तोयनिधिः तोयानि निधीयन्तेऽस्मिन् । अवगाह्यAccording to the grammarian Bhaguri the 3 of 374 and 3174 is dropped; and according to the परिभाषा &amp;rsquo; आचार्य महणे च विभाषा qwqr&amp;rsquo; i, e. when a rule is stated mentioning the name of an A&amp;rsquo;chârys, the rule becomes optional; so fruri, afya, &amp;amp;o. See El. Gr. p. 220. foot-note. Cf. qaiqcwgaramız: ergяræ S&amp;rsquo;âk, VII. p. 100. अश्वाध्यधुर्वसुमतीमतिरांचमानाः । Sis. V. 4. मन्दारमाला हरिणा faner S&amp;rsquo;ak. VII. 2. fa mý saá ígag; Bhatti. III. 47.&#xA;i&#xA;वितत्य कवचं पिना; मानदण्डःThe great length of the mountain justifies the Utprekshâ. —may be taken to mean, as done by the Com. (1) measure; or (2) the instrument of measuring. Or #a may mean the whole measure, according to the Sruti T पृथिवी तावन्मात्री हिमालयः । यावन्मात्री हिमालयस्तावन्मात्रा पृथिवी ।&#xA;(2)&#xA;(Sl.) 2 सर्वशैलाः -For the comp. seo Malli. and H. Gr. $ 227. ( g ). वत्सं - shows the importance of Himalaya as ranking next To Meru. मेरी - According to the Puránas Meru, the home of the gods, forms the central point of the earth, all the planets revolving round it and is in shape like the cup or seed-vessel of a lotus, the different Dwipas spreading out from it like leaves. It is formed of gold, having jewels on it, and is 84000 Yojanas in height, 16000 of which are buried in the earth. The Ganges falls from heaven on its peak and thence flows to the sea.&#xA;Its summit is the residence of Brahman and the meeting place of the gods, Rshis, Gandharvas &amp;amp;c. मेरुर्मध्ये भुवनानां व भर्ता Kal. P. मेरुस्तु शुशुभे दिव्यो राजवत्समधिष्ठितः । आदित्यतरुणाभासो विधूम इव पावकः ॥ योजनानां सहस्राणि चतुरशीतिरुच्छ्रितः । प्रविष्टः षोडशाधस्तादष्टाविंशतिविंशतिः । विस्तारात्रिगुणस्तस्य परिणाहः समन्ततः ॥ Mat. P. The learned author of the A. H. V. shows that Meru is the terrestrial North Pole and quotes the following verses from the Mah. Bhár. Van, ch. 163 as describing its Polar characteristics - एनं त्वहरहरु सूर्याचन्द्रमसी ध्रुवं । प्रदक्षिणमुपावृस्य कुरुतः कुरुनन्दन ॥ ज्योतींषि चाप्यशेषेण सर्वाण्यनध सर्वतः । परियन्ति महाराज गिरिराजं प्रदक्षिणम् || स्वतेजसा तस्य नगोत्तमस्य महोपधीनां च तथा प्रभावात् । विभक्तभावो न बभूष कश्विदहनिशानां पुरुषप्रवीर । बभूव रात्रिदिवसश्च तेषां संवत्सरेणैव समानरूपः ॥ Seo A H. V. pp. 67, 69.&#xA;1&#xA;पृथूपदिष्टाम्Pointed out as possessing such and such characteristics by Prthu. Prthu was a mighty king, the son of Vena, son of Anga. Vena, by his wicked deeds and blasphemous language towards Vishnu, offended the sages who killed him with their Huñkáras (इति तेऽसत्कृतास्तेन द्विजाः पण्डितमानिना । भमायां मव्ययाञ्चायां तस्मै विदुर चुकुधुः ॥ हन्यतां हन्यतामेष पापः प्रकृतिदारुणः ॥ इत्थं व्यवसिता हन्तुमृषयो रूढमन्यवः । निजघ्नुहुंकतैर्वेनं हतमच्युतनिन्दया || B. P. IV. 4. 30. 31, 34.) The sages afterwards rubbed the right arm of the dead king and from it sprang the majestic Prthu glowing like Agni. He was immediately declared king. From him the earth received the name Pṛthvi. The subjects of Prthu being troubled by a famine applied to the king for the edible fruits and plants which the earth had withheld. Pṛthu took up his bow to compel the earth to yield the supply. She, however, fled in the form of a cow but submit. ted to the king afterwards and promised to yield the supply if a suitable calf were given to her so as to be able to secrete milk Prthu, thereupon, made Svayambhu Manu the calf,&#xA;(3)&#xA;milked the earth, and received the milk thus got in his hand. from which were produced corn, vogetables, fruits &amp;amp;c. For other particulars see Apte&amp;rsquo;s Dic. ; B. P. IV. chs. 15-18. The Earth was also milked in their turns by the sages, monntains &amp;amp;c. Cf. इति प्रियं हितं वाक्यं भुव आदाय भूपतिः । वत्सं कृत्वा मनुं पाणावदुहceकलोषधीः ॥ तथा परे च सर्वत्र सारमाददते बुधाः । ततोन्ये च यथाकामं बुदुहुः पृथुभाविताम् ।। ऋषये दुदुदुर्देवीमिन्द्रियेष्वथ सत्तम । वत्सं चहस्पति कृत्वा पयश्छन्दोमयं शुचि ॥गिरयो हिमवदत्सा नाना धातून् स्वसानुषु । सर्वे स्वमुख्यवत्सेन वे स्वे पात्रे पृथक् पयः । सर्वकामदुघां पृथ्वीं दुदुः पृथुभाविताम् ॥ B P IV. 18.12-20. Also Mat. P. गिरिभिर्वसुधा दुग्धा रत्नानि विविधानि च । औषधानि च दिव्यानि दोग्धा मेरुर्महाबलः ॥ वत्सोऽभूद्धि#aita &amp;amp;c. Sl, quoted in S. D. as an instance of the fault of the personal pronoun being understood.&#xA;(Sl.) 3. farofa-Merges in, is lost sight of i. e. is not noticed or taken into account इन्दु-इन्दु is ordinarily derived as उनस्यमृतमिति or उनत्ति चन्द्रिकया भुवनमिति, fr. उन्द् to ooze and the Unadi aff. उ. In the Veda, however it is said to mean a bright or sparkling drop of the Soma juice; ef. gare इन्दवः । Rg. I. 16. 16. It then came to signify &amp;amp; round little body and finally became a name of the moon like the wood Soma itself एको हि &amp;amp;c. cf the humorous retort on this (said to be composed by Achyutarao Modak, the celebrated rhetorician of Nasik) &amp;ndash;एको हि दोषो गुणसंनिपाते निमज्जतीन्दोरिति यो बभाषे 1 न तेन दृष्टं कविना यथैको (नूनं न दृष्टं कविना पितेन * ) दारिद्र्यदोषो गुणराशि (कोटि) नाशी ॥ Cf. रहितरत्नचयान्न शिलोच्चयानपलताभवना न दरीभुवः । बिपुलिनाम्बुरुहा न सरिद्वधूरकुसुमान् दधतं न महीरुहः | Kir. V. 10.&#xA;अद्भयः सरन्ती-&#xA;(Sl.) 4. अप्सरस : - The courtesans of Heaven स्वप्सरसः sprung from water : so called because, according to the Rámáyana, they came out of the churued ocean-अप्सु निर्मथनादेव रसात्तस्माद्वरस्त्रियः । उत्पेतुर्मनुजश्रेष्ठ तस्मादप्सरसोऽभवन् ॥ Or because they are supposed to bathe frequently. Although the word is generally used in the plural, it is also found used in the sing. (as in the Bhashya on Pán. VIII. 4. 47 ) and dual ( अप्सरसाविति श्रुतिनिर्देशात् ); cf. Vik. अनप्सरेव प्रतिभासि According to the Mah. Bhár. they are the daughters of Kashyapa and&#xA;It is said that the poet Gatakarpara being vanquished by Kálidasa in his Nalodaya as regards the composition of stanzas containing 4448 had this fling at the latter on this Sloka of the Kumårsambhava. कविनापि तेन may also be read as कवि - नापितेन ( &amp;amp; barber ).&#xA;(4)&#xA;Pradhā-इमं स्वप्सरसां वंशं विदितं पुण्यलक्षणम्। प्रधासूत महाभागा देवika: g For the principal Apsarases see note on III. 17. विभ्रमार्थ मण्डनानि विभ्र० विभ्रम is used here in the sense of From &amp;lsquo;amorous sport.&#xA;Decorations which added grace to their amorous gestures. The second sense given by Malli. viz. the misplacing of ornaments on the person through hurry and confusion does not seem to be natural, Cf. विलासिनीविभ्रमदन्तपत्रम् Rag. VI. 17. बलाहक &amp;ndash;&amp;amp; compound of the पृषोदरादि class. The comp. gāzt ( qaa 377 ) is formed by the dropping of a; so comp. of irregular formation is explained by classing it under the head of garzy (Pán. VI. 3. 109); here aft is changed to ब and व to ल. अकालसन्ध्याम् - Twilight ont of the proper time. The large mass of red minerals imparted a red hue to the clouds over-hanging it, so that to a looker on from a distance the whole scone, the mineral-covered peaks together with the alouds, presented an aspect of the evening sky.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;sI. 1. तारक - A demon, son of Vajranakha and Varánji. Brahmá conferred upon him a boon that he would not be killed by any one except a child seven days old. Kârtikeya slew tho demon on the 7th day of his birth. दिवौकसः - Fr. दिव + ओक; if derived from दिव् the form will be दिवोकम् ( or दिवौकस if classed under पृषोदरादि as Malli saya ). तुरासाह-Lit, who overpowers or defeats the mighty or impetuous बेगवन्तं साहयति अभिभवतिः or तुरा may mean quickly; fr. तुर + सह Cau + किए। अन्येषामपि दृश्यते । Pán. VI. 4. 137 इति पूर्वपदस्य दीर्घः । स्वायंभुवं Here the ऊ of स्वयंभू does not take Guna substitute as it should by the rule &amp;lsquo;ओर्गुण:&amp;rsquo; ( The उ or ऊ of a Oha base takes Gana before a Taddhita affix. Pán. VI. 4. 116) by the Maxim संज्ञापूर्वको विधिरनित्य:rule is not universally applicable when what it teaches is expressed by a technical term such as by गुण here ). See Malli. Cf. एतस्मिन्नन्तरे काले तारकेण दिवौकसः । आजी पराजिता आसन शकदर्पविघातिना । तदा सर्वे तुरासाहं कृत्वाये हतविक्रमाः । स्वायंभुवं ययौ धामं सत्यलोकमिति श्रुतम् ॥ S&amp;rsquo; P; also Rag. X. 5.&#xA;omen; for अव्याक्षेपो आविस् has optionally&#xA;(Sl.) 2. आविरभूद्वह्मा - This was a good भविष्यन्त्याः कार्यसिद्धेर्हि लक्षणम् । Rag. X 6 गतिसंज्ञा (ie is treated as a prep. or उपसर्ग) and then must precede the root connected with it. When it is a mere निपात it may stand apart from a root; of वारुणीमदविशङ्कमथाविश्वक्षुषोऽभवदसाविव रागः । Sia X 18. सुप्तपद्यानां - The lotuses correspond to the faces of the gods. For &amp;amp; similar idea comp. सुप्तमीन( 29 )&#xA;इव हृदः । Rag I. 73. दीधितिमानिव – The comparison implies&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(61.) 1. मघवन् — an epithet of Indra. Originally thie waa a word of regular formation. fr. ĦĦ a gift, present or wealth and बत् or वन्; one possessing riches or distributing gifts; the whole then signifying-the munificent Indra i. e. the sun, the bestower of plentiful rain and thereby of wealth.&amp;rsquo; In postVedic times the term came to be applied to Indra and explained # महाते पूज्यते इति irregularly derived by the Uus. St. श्वत्रुक्षन् &amp;amp;c., from महू to adore and the af. अन् (कनिन् ) with the augment हृ.&#xA;त्रिदशा: - The gods. जन्मसत्ताविनाशास्यास्तिस्रो दशा येषां or तृतीया यौवनाखया वृक्षा येषाम्; or the gods taken collectively, ses Malli.,( 49 )&#xA;thirty standing for 33. According to the S&amp;rsquo;at. B. the gods are 33कतमे ते त्रयस्त्रिंशदिति अष्टौ वसव एकादश रुद्रा द्वादशादित्यास्त एकत्रिंशदिन्द्रश्चैव प्रजापतिश्व त्रयस्त्रिंशदिति । प्रयोजना &amp;amp;o. - प्रयोजनमपेक्षतेऽसौ प्रयोजनापेक्षी तस्य भावस्तत्ता तया ।&#xA;(Sl.) 2. आसन०-Malli. remarks 387 &amp;amp;c. The meaning of S&amp;rsquo;esha is कारकप्रातिपदिकार्थव्यतिरिक्तः स्वस्वामिभावादिसम्बन्धः । Sid. Kau.; gaga—a with q and q is A&amp;rsquo;tm. in the sense of &amp;rsquo; beginning &amp;lsquo;; see com समर्थो तुल्यार्थी प्रारम्भेनयोस्तुल्यार्थता | Sid. Kau, bnt मकामति goes ; उपक्रामति comes. समर्थ means तुल्यार्थ ; when tho root क्रम् with में or उप has the same meaning viz. зmen, it takes æg (is Aʼtm.)&#xA;(Sl.) 3. arafag-He who knows the special merit of a person. ज्ञातविशेष इत्यनेनात्मन इतरेभ्य उत्कर्षो द्योतितः । Ohir By using this epithet Kama compliments Indra on his readiness to appreciate merit and to show respect to those who deserve it. He says आज्ञापय as ho knows that Indra could not have thought of him unless he had some business in view requiring his special service. Oh yeah, agua Vik. I. Hero fa should not have been compounded as get is left out; but as the connection can be plainly seen the comp. may be allowed ; and bonco Malli&amp;rsquo;s remark सांपक्षत्वे &amp;amp;c. लोकेषु - by this, Káma shows that he has power over the three worlds. wygg-Kâma feels particularly flattered, as he, of all the gods, was specially remembered by his chief. Ilis speech is quito in keeping with court language. #iga-Malli. notices the reading it and remarks that if it is admitted an effort should be made to explain it by attaching a causal sense to the root without the termination, for if faa be added the form will be ga¿faga.&#xA;SI. 4. quifgm-Having been often employed in similar duties, this is Káma&amp;rsquo;s first thought. Indra is often represented as being alarmed whenever a mortal practises unusual austerities lest he might aim at his post. Cf. - तदन्यसमाधिभीरुत्वं देवानां Sak ; चरतः किल दुश्वरं तपस्तृणबिन्दोः परिशंकितः पुरा । प्रजिघाय समाधिभेदिनीं हरिरस्में हरिणीं सुतंगनाम् ॥ Rag. VIII. 79 ; also XIII. 39, 42, ava-Malli, takes this in the sense of qĦ: but without stating authority; it may be taken in the sense of &amp;lsquo;ged &amp;lsquo;-will fully be ( waia ); or butter with भवति giving it a future sense, by the rule यावत्पुरानिपातयोर्लट् । कार्मुक-कर्मण प्रभवति इति ( कर्मन् + उक ).&#xA;L. N. 5&#xA;( 50 )&#xA;Bl. 5. असंमत: &amp;amp;c. -Now he says Even if a man does not seek your post, but merely aims at Moksha and has not your approval, him, I will fetter down to the world. मुक्तिमार्ग प्रपन:&amp;ndash;seeking ब्रह्मविद्या, having renounued the world. See supra II. 51. Cf. विज्ञानार्थं स गुरुमेवाभिगच्छेत् समित्पाणिः श्रोत्रियं ब्रह्मनिष्ठस् । Mund. I. 2. 12. ब्रह्मविदामोति पर Tsit. II. 1. 1. न जायते म्रियते वा विपश्चित् । Káth. II. 18. &amp;amp;c. आरेचित - Cf. D. K. रेचित भूलतेर पाब्रवीक्षितैः &amp;amp; चतुर -beautiful, engaging, charming (f I 47; V. 49, असंमत: कस्तवेन्द्र मुक्तिमार्गमपेक्षते । तं सुन्दरीकटाक्षैस्तु यन्नाम्याज्ञापयस्व मे ॥ 8. P.&#xA;(Sl.)&#xA;उशनस् - Sukracharya, son of Bhriga and preceptor of the demons, In the Vedic as well as post-Vedic literature the epithet Kävya &amp;rsquo;the wise is applied to him. He is also known as a writer on civil and religious law and is one of the authorities cited on civil polity. मीर्ति - Niti is used here in a wider sense-that which gives rules for the sonduct of human affairs or regulates the daily life of individuals enabling them to secure з and without infringement of religious law. राग -Love for varnal pleasures ( clouding reason ) अर्थधर्मोalso धर्मार्थी by the Vartik. (on Pan. 2. II. 31 ) धर्मादिष्यनियमः । Sole attention to Kåma would destroy the other two. These are the three of the four objects of human pursuit, the fourth being fìm, figarf4-obstruct, overpower, i. s. whom shall I make a helpless sensualist: कस्य शोरपि इरे धर्मार्थो पीडयाम्यहम् | 8&amp;rsquo;. P.&#xA;(Sl.) 7. दुःखशीलां -Austerely aticking to her cow of; or habitually suffering the misery or hardships of; of दुःखशीके auftraà S&amp;rsquo;âk, IV. Org: may mean qusi atë qet: giving तपस्विजने&#xA;दुःखकरं शीलं यस्याः pain to others on account of स्वयंग्राह० By the rule विभाषा ग्रहः, ण ( अ ) in added to ग्रह in the sense of an alligator&amp;rsquo; only, as the optionality is fixed, as remarked by Vâmana-sqaftarविभाषा बेयम्। अलवरे नित्यं ग्राहः । ज्योतिषि नेष्यते तत्र ग्रह एम। This view is held by Haradatta and Bhattoji also; hence Malli.&amp;rsquo;s defence of this appears to be questionable. Some say-fagur: कवयः । ग्राह may be derived by affixing पत्र or अत्र ( स्वार्थण्यम्तादच ) स्वयं प्राहो ग्रहणं यस्याः साः प्रहे ग्राह: Amsra; now see oom. Malli. refers here to Indra&amp;rsquo;s seduction of Ahalys.&#xA;(Sl.) 8. कामिन&amp;ndash;भूयान् कामोस्य इन् shows excess; seo Gr. मलुप् aft; foot-note-भूमनिन्दाप्रशंसा &amp;amp;c. सुरता. सुरते अपराधसारात् । कोपना -कुध्यति तच्छीला इडा - Repentance for having&#xA;।&#xA;( 51 )&#xA;slighted the prostration. प्रवालशय्या 016 of the usual appliances for allaying the torment caused by love-affection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Sl.) 1. मोहपरायणा - Who was solely in the power of or under the protection of प्रतिपादयिष्यता - wishing to explain to her or make her understand; hence to make her experience; प्रतिपादनं तु दाने प्रतिपत्ती प्रबोधने । इति मेदिनी ।&#xA;(Sl.) 2. अवधानपरे - attentively fixed was in. sreq-a&amp;ndash;utterly i, e, for ever.&#xA;प्रलय the swoon she Cf. अत्यन्त लुप्त प्रियदर्शनेन Rag. XIV. 49. सा चात्यन्तमदर्शनं नयनयोर्यातेति कोयं विधिः । Vik. IV. 2.&#xA;(Sl.) 3. अयि - see Malli.; कोमलामन्त्रणे वा. Sl quoted in the D. R. as an instance of ( इष्टनाशात्करुण ) the Karupa rasa consequent on the destruction of a beloved person ( इष्टनाशादनिष्टामी शोकात्मा करुणो नु तम् । ).&#xA;(Sl.) 4. समदुः खामित्र &amp;amp;c. -स्थली by Lakshana means the &amp;lsquo;plants and creatures in that place,&amp;rsquo; poetically represented as sharing Rati&amp;rsquo;s grief; cf. अकरोत्पृथिवीरुहानपि स्स्रुतशाखारसवाष्पदुर्दिनान् । Rag. VIII. 70. गुरुतरशोकोपहता कुररीव प्रियवियोगमापन्ना | आक्रन्ददानादं बापस्नपितोन्नतस्तनी बाला || Par. P. III. 11. For the idos of also Sak. वयोपस्थितवियोगस्य तपोवनस्यापि समवस्था दृश्यते । उद्गलितदर्भकवला मृग्यः परित्यक्तनर्तना मयूराः । अपसृतपाण्डुपत्रा मुञ्चन्यभ्रूणीव लताः ॥ IV. 12. 600 also Rag. XIV. 69.&#xA;81 5 उपमान Standards of comparison of 1. 36. उपमानस्यापि सखे प्रत्युपमानं वपुस्तस्याः | Vik. II. 3. विलासिनां विलासः अस्यास्तीति विलासी. विलास is defined as प्रियसमीपगमन यः स्थानासनगमनfrotray विकारोऽकस्माच्च क्रोधस्मितचमत्कारमुखविक्लवनं स विलासः .. the sudden change of place, posture, gait, or look as also the manifestation of feigned anger, smile &amp;amp;c. on the approach of or on approaching &amp;amp; lover. न विदीर्ये &amp;amp;c. - Which she ought to have done as a Pativrată; cf. the S&#39;1. nafa giąà &amp;amp;c. quoted by Malli. further on (sl. 33). Cf. the similar thoughts of Bita-मनो मे न बिना रामावत्पुस्फोट सहस्रधा । &amp;amp;c. Bhatti XIV. 66; also 57, 58; and infra, notes on sl. 21.&#xA;अधि&#xA;(Sl.) 6. त्वदधीन-वार्य आधे त्वदधीनं; the all. ख ( ईन ) is always added when з forms the latter part of a Loc. Tat. क्षणभित्र ०Cf. कथमेकपदे निरागसं जनमाभाष्यमिमं न मन्यसे । Rag. VIII. 48. सेतु सौहृद is here compared to Setu or &amp;amp; dam, the common ground of comparison being, as remarked by Malli.,&#xA;(68)&#xA;furge the one keeping together Rati and Madana, the other, water and the lotus-plaut. -The word u being&#xA;सौहृद सुहृदय mentioned in the gaą group takes з; and by virtue of this its af and the substitute of a for take place by the&#xA;हृत् हृदय rule is changed to before the word, the affixes यत् and अण and before लास&amp;rsquo; if हृदय be changed to हृद् in the sense of &amp;lsquo;a friend&amp;rsquo; by Pán. V. 4, 150, then 30 boing added the form willie सौहार्द See cont. The absence of the उत्तरपदवृद्धि ( . . हार ) should rather be explained by the general maxim és विधिरनित्यः ।&#xA;Sl.&#xA;(7.) कृतवानसि विप्रियं - Cf मनसापि न विप्रियं मया कृतपूर्व तव किं जहासि माम् । Rag. VIII. 2. प्रतिकूलं प्रतीपं कुलात्। Cf. When was the hour, I ever contradicted your desire&amp;rsquo;, Shaks. Henry VIII. II. 4.&#xA;SL. 8. Rati means to say that knowingly she had given Káma no offence. But in their love-sports she had sometimes taken liberty with him and that might have displeased him. maraisàg-Lovers are often represented as misnaming their sweet-hearts or wives calling them by the name uppermost in their minds through absentmindedness while lost in thoughts about other Indies. Cf. गोत्रेषु स्खलितस्तदा भवति च व्रीडाविलक्षश्विरम् । Sakh. VI. 5. अनं ज णिमित्तं भट्टा उक्कण्ठिदो ताए इथ्थिआए णामधेएण भट्टिणा देवी आलविदा | Vik. II. लोलुपं बत मनो ममति तं गोत्रfaraisaqueran: Rag. XIX. 24 बन्धनं - - -17. मेखलाभिरसकच्च&#xA;बन्धनं वश्ञ्चयन् प्रणयिनीरवाप सः । Rag. XIX. 17.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;प्रियेषु &amp;amp; - सुभगाया भावः सौभाग्यं good fortune. Beauty has for its fruit good fortune as regards the husband or a&#xA;&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;love&amp;rsquo; i.&#xA;if a woman&amp;rsquo;s beauty attracts her husband and makes him love her then only that can be called beauty; otherwise it is useless, howsoever great it may be in the eyes of others. Cf. infra - स्त्रीणt प्रियालोकफलो हि वेशः । VHH 29,&#xA;(61.) 2. भवन्ध्यरूप - The negation here is prominent ( प्रसज्यमतिषेध ), and so it should not have been compounded; soo our note on Rag. 1. or Meg. II. 2. But according to the Bhashyakara such नन् may be compounded मसज्यप्रतिषेधपि न समास इष्यते । or the coup. way be taken as न वन्ध्यमवन्ध्यं, अवन्ध्यं च तट्टपं च तस्य भावः । 81 quoted in Sar K as an instance of तपश्वरणादिजन्मा नैमित्तिकानुरागः ।&#xA;★&#xA;SI. 3. गिरीशo Some read as गिरीशं प्रति सकमानसां in which case प्रति is &amp;quot; कर्मप्रवचनीय governing गिरीश. Whon the whole is taken as a comp. fa is an Upasarga after which is changed to पू. गिरीश -the lord of the mountain Kailasn.&#xA;गिरियां supra. 1. 60.&#xA;See note on&#xA;83&#xA;(Sl.) 4. मनीषिता: Such as the mind would long for, would satisfy the cravings of the mind. Mark the Samdhi (मनस् + ईषित); see.com. &amp;ndash;Lit. where is the one-where is the other; hence by Kâku (intonation) this means-how great is the distance between the two; the two how uuequal ! The repetition of shows the great disparity between the two. Cf. सूर्यप्रभवो वंशक चाल्पविषया मतिः Rag. I. ; क भूपतीनां चरितं क जन्तवः । Kir. I. 6; also infra. 73. पतत्रिन - पतति इति from पत् + अत्रिन्. Cf. परुषस्तपोविशेषस्तव पुनरङ्गं शिरीषसुकुमारम् । व्यवसितमेतत्कठिनं पार्वति तदुष्करमिति प्रतिभाति ॥ Par. P. III. 16. इति स्वतनयावाक्यं श्रुत्वा तु पितने मुने । ऊचतुर्दुःखितो भूखा बाष्पगदया गिरा । तस्मात्त्रं भक्तियुक्तेन पूजयस्व गृहे शिवम् । उमा गच्छ बनं घोरं सर्वविघ्नास्पदं सदा ॥ 8&amp;rsquo; P.&#xA;Sl. 5 श्रवेच्छां - This is proferable to the other readings as it explains why her mother failed to dissuade her from going to practies penance. ईप्सित P. P. p. of the Desid. of आपू. निम्नाभिमुखं - Dissolve निम्नस्याभिमुखम् । प्रतीपर्यत - A Denomi. verb from प्रतीप.&#xA;(61.) 6. मनोरथज्ञं - Who knew her cherished desire and who was therefore expected to grant the permission readily.&#xA;( 75 )&#xA;मनस्विनी&#xA;aftanf-of sound judgment, thoughtful, i. e., who knew when and how to make a request.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SI. 1. मन्दिवंश Sent as a messenger, i. a sent &amp;amp; message through her. प्रमाणीक्रियताम् should be approached or referred to as an anthority (not being so approached before ), i, e.. should be formally applied to for my hand and his consent obtained (the father being the proper authority for the disposal of his daughter in marriage).अभ्यासे-&#xA;(89)&#xA;Sl. 2. व्याहृत० – व्याहृतः सन्देशो यस्याः । निभृता प्रिये - निभृता appears to mean keeping quiet; silently waiting for her espousal by S&amp;rsquo;iva. Thereby indicating her modesty; one Com, says सलज्जत्वाद्विनीता चूतयष्टि: - should rather means young mango tree (cf. 3). spa-noar at hand. The meaning isParvati having sent word to Siva as to the course he was to adopt stood silently waiting for her marriage. just as a young mango-tree stands expecting the advent of summer (when it is about to set in ) sending the call for it through the Kokila. The notes of the cuckoo always herald the spring. great see Malli.. it is better to take qrgar as Instr. sing, as suggested by Mallinâtha.&#xA;SJ. 3. ufqWith difficulty (as he was now irresistibly drawn towards her, being wou over by her unflinching devotion and love); see Malli. - For their names see notes on I, 16. salíādara, e. having astral bodies ag apart from the physical ones. The Rshis in their astral forms&#xA;constitute the constellation of stars called &amp;rsquo; Ursa Major&amp;rsquo; or the - Great Bear&amp;rsquo; of दिग्भ्यो निमन्त्रिताश्चैनमभिजग्मुर्महर्षयः । न भौमान्येव froण्यानि हित्वा ज्योतिर्मयान्यपि । Rag. XV.50.&#xA;Sl. 4. argalar-Arundhati, wife of Vas ishtha was one of the nine daughters of Kardama Prajápati by Devahúti. She is regarded as the highest patteru of conjugal excellence and wifely devotion and is so invoked by the bridegroom at nuptial ceremonies. The Rshis are invariably associated with Arundhati and are always so invoked. Astronomically represented she is the smallest star in the constellation Urea Major. -explains why they readily appeared before S&amp;rsquo;iva.&#xA;S1. 5. faza&#xA;Quarter-elephants are described as bathing in the celestial Ganges; cf. Rag. I. 78.&#xA;(Sl.) 6. asai Malli. understands by this the Sanyásâs&amp;rsquo;rama or the fourth order in the religious life of a Brahmaṇa and then takes it to refer to Vánaprasthás&amp;rsquo;rama by Lakshanâ; see his remarks. This, however, is not necessary, as the abandonment of wife, the sacred thread, &amp;amp;c., is not necessary in every kind of Sanyása. By Pravrajyâ we might understand the विद्वत्संन्यास, such as was practised by Yajnavalkys and others. ( सम्यगनुष्ठितेः श्रवणमननं निदिध्यासतैः परतत्वं विदितवद्भिः&#xA;( 90 )&#xA;2¶¤¤à] Íâæ-á-arg:1). See also Bg. VI. 1. 2; XVIII. 2. Looking to the general drift of the sl. it appears better, however, to take gap in the sense of &amp;lsquo;going, motion.&amp;rsquo; The Rahis had jewels, gold &amp;amp;c. on, and so looked like the desiregranting trees in motion. If wo accept Malli.&amp;rsquo;s sense the comparison to Kalpa-trees becomes meaningless. Cf. ¿¤¤èz इव जङ्गमकल्पवृक्ष: Vik. V. 19.&#xA;Sl. 8. आसक्तबा० -आसक्का या बाहुलता ( scil of the sages तया उद्धतया भुवा – The earth which was submerged in the oceanic water was drawn up by Vishnu, assuming the form of a Boar. Cf. Gitagovinda वसति दशनशिखरे धरणी तब लग्ना | शशिनि कलङ्ककलेव निमग्रा । केशव धृतशुकररूप जय जगदीश हरे | See B. P. III. 13.&#xA;Sl.&#xA;(9.) qqqa-Mark the root-sense-carrying forward (the work of), completing, geraar:-ger ar: 1 See faaraa supra IV. 46. art: &amp;amp;c.—The seven sages were the mind-born sons ( qonqfas) of Brahmâ created for the purpose of carrying on the work of creation. &amp;ldquo;The descendants of the daughters of Daksha were married to those Brahmarshis. Mârkandeya was the son of Mrikandu the grandson of Bhrigu. The 49 fires, the 60,000 Válakhilyas, &amp;amp;c., were the progeny of these sages. V. P. I, 10. &amp;quot; Des pande.&#xA;तपस्विनः&#xA;(Sl.) 10. ait:-i. e. they kept their minds under control although enjoying the fruits of their penance.&#xA;(Sl.) 12. ईश्वर:-fr. ईश् + वरच by स्थेशभासपिसकसो वरच Pan. III. 2. 175. स्थावर, भास्वर, पेस्वर &amp;amp;c. स्त्री पुमान् - Cf. शिशुत्वं स्त्रैणं वा भवतु ननु वन्द्यासि जगताम् । गुणाः पूजास्थानं गुणिषु न च लिंगं न च वयः । Ettar. IV. 11,&#xA;(Sl.) 13. दारार्थ - दारभ्य इति धर्म्य -lit not departing from, keeping to, duty; see com. Similarly qq, 2 &amp;amp;o. quî—is the fem. when the meaning is she who shares in the fruit of the sacrificial acts performed by the husband&amp;rsquo;. que-For the precept is सत्रीको धर्ममाचरेत् । of Mah, Bhá भार्या मूलं त्रिवर्गस्य भार्या मूलं तरिष्यतः ।&#xA;(Sl.) 14. r-i, e. by the god of religious duties or righteousness (depending upon married life ), and not by Râga or sensual desire. -S&amp;rsquo;iva in the form of ferfa; of wat falagdà an: Bháv. P.; fr. -f the destroyer; this socounts for the fear of Káma. पदं का० पदं कृ to set foot on; hence to bring under influence; cf. III. 33, V. 21 &amp;amp;c. Cf.&#xA;(91)&#xA;Char. प्राग्धर्मेण प्रार्थितो ब्रह्मा यहा हरो गौरी परिणेष्यति तदा स्मरः स्वं वपुः प्राप्स्यतीति शापान्तं चक्रे । अता धर्मेण गौरीं प्रत्युद्यमः कारितो न तु रांगण |&#xA;(61.) 15. जगद्गुरु&amp;ndash;गुरु may meun (1) the father ie creator of the world; cf जगतः पितरौ वन्दे &amp;amp;c. Rag. I. 1; or ( 2 ) adorable to अनूचान - one who has studied the Vedas with their aiigas (accessary works) and is able to expound them; see com. It is formed from बच with अनु with the affix आन ( कानच् ) added zäft, azımgaza zarra Sid. Kau. The six angas areशिक्षा कल्पो व्याकरणं निरुक्तं छन्दसां चयः । ज्योतिषामयनं चैव बेदाङ्गानि षडेव तु ॥&#xA;་&#xA;Sl. 16. तस्य - १. कुत्स्नस्य तस्य कर्मणः or पृथगन्वयादेकवचनम्विपर्क -has pre-eminently borne fruit.&#xA;SI. 17 मनोरथ - Lit, the car of the mind; hence the mind moving from one object to another like a car; hence desire. -स्थावि०&amp;ndash;beyond the province of desire not to be thought of even by the mind. qaifaqys—may meau-the object of our minds i, e. thyself; or (we have been made) the object of thy mind thou having remembered us.&#xA;(Sl.) 18. कृतिनां प्रशस्तं कृतमस्यास्तीति: here इन shows excellence; who has a good stock of merit, blessed. नावत् surely ( अवधारणे ) त्रह्म - the Vedas; cf. the Sruti निश्वसितमस्य षदाः, and the Bad. Sutra शास्त्रयोनित्वात् I. 1. 3.&#xA;(Sl.) 20. अर्क - fr. अ 10. P. to praise अयंत; or fr. अर्च, च् being changed to by Unádi. III. 40.&#xA;(Sl.) 21. विरूपाक्ष – This is variously derived as विविधानि रविचन्द्राग्निरूपाणि अक्षीण्यस्य ; or विरूपेष्वपि अक्षि कृपादृष्टिर्यस्य; or विविधरूपाणि विविधरूपेषु वा अक्षाणि इन्द्रियाणि यस्य । Any of these will do here.&#xA;(Sl.) 22 साक्षात् - e. in a form perceptible to the senses. अञ्जसा -( Inst, sing. of अअम् used as an adv. ) &amp;ldquo;orrectly: as regards thy true nature. तत्वत्वद्धाअसा द्वयोः | Amara. Cf. याथार्थ्य वेद कस्तव । Rag. X. 24. न धियां पथि वर्तस - Cf. यतो वाचो निवर्तन्ते अपाप्य मनसा सह । Tait Up.&#xA;अव्यक्त&#xA;4&#xA;(Sl.) 23. व्यक्तं - The distinct or manifested world ( developed from or the indistinct originating principle). Cf. अव्यक्तो व्यक्तकारणम् । Rag. X 18 भाग:not a portion or part but a phase of. Thou art the same in these three capacities; ef. the Smrti-बह्मत्वे सृजते लोकान् विष्णुत्वे पालयत्यपि । रुद्रत्वे संहरत्येष तिस्रोवस्थाः स्वयंभुवः ॥&#xA;( 92 )&#xA;Sl. 24. सुमहती - गुह्यार्थबोधनाद्दुर्लभा । Cha&amp;rsquo;r.; one to which we caunot aspire just now.&#xA;Sl. 25 इन्दुःउनच्यमृतमति irregularly derived fr. उन्द to o0ze, and the Unádi aft, उः or उनत्ति केदयति चन्द्रिका भुवनम् । Originally meant a sparkling drop of the Soma juice or&#xA;geg the Soma juice itself; cf. garage: Rgv. I. 16, 6. It then meant a small round body and finally came to mean the moon when Soma became a name of the moon.&#xA;Sl. 26. स्वार्था न मे - Cr लोकानुग्रह एवैको हेतुस्ते जन्मकर्मणोः । Rag. X. 31. -surely, giâfî: &amp;amp;c.-The eight forms are: the five elements, the sun, moon and the sacrificer; 200 S&amp;rsquo;ák. I. 1. They are thus given in the Bháv. P. qafu fgfagda an: 1 भवाय जलमूर्तये नमः । रुद्रायाग्निमूर्तये नमः । उग्राय वायुमूर्तये नमः । भीमायाकाशमूर्तये नमः । पशुपतये यजमानमूर्तये नमः | महादेवाय सोममूर्तये नमः । Éma14 gýgào 74: All these are for the welfare of the world. Sl. 27. -The Chátaka bird has wholly to depend upon the clouds for water: cf. Bhar, agðurìdifā svi a da: S&amp;rsquo;ivo means by the simile that the gods are quite helpless and have solely to depend upon him for a deliverer and hence his seemingly strange procedure,&#xA;www.com&#xA;Sl. 28. आत्मज ०&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/shaivam/kAvyam/padyam/kAlidAsaH_kumAra-sambhavam/TIkAH/kAle/03_NOTES/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SI. 1. ओषधीनामधिपस्य -The moon is called the lord of herbs as they thrive under the influence of the lunar rays. Cf. सोमेनादित्या बलिनः सोमेन पृथिवी मही । Rg. X 85 2 commenting on which Sáyana says - अमृत से केनौषध्यभिवृद्धया पृथिव्या बलवत्वम्&#xA;( 103 )&#xA;I&#xA;Also aataeû qat usd aur aalaqt ar: 1 dictauiai fagmıggt a जनमेजय । II. V. and बीजोषधीनां तोयानां राजाभूदग्रजन्मनाम् ॥ Ka. Kh. According to some it was in the lant, that was originally regarded as the king of plants, and when by a curious misapplication Soma became a name of the moon, the latter came to be called the king of plants.&#xA;rf-The seventh zodiacal sign or house in a diagram representing the aspect of heavens at the time of a person&amp;rsquo;s birth from his natal sign (the one just rising above the horizon at the moment) and which is the house of the wife or husband. a g-purity, it being free from any adverse influence exerted by a planet such as the moon &amp;amp;c.; see Malli ̧ Cf. पापग्रहाच्चन्द्रो यदि सप्तमस्थः स्यात्तदा जामित्रवेधो नाम दोषान्तरं जायते । Also रविमन्दकुजाकान्तं मृगाङ्कात्सप्तमं त्यजेत् । विवाहयात्राचूडास गृहकर्मgaga u Some consider this word to be a contracted form of , the seventh sign indicating the future good luck of one&amp;rsquo;s wife. But it may be directly derived from If [which means a Vadhú or daughter-in-law. See Manus. III. 57; Mah. Bhár. XIII. 15; or a woman in general; see Brh. Sam. 74. 10;) and (Fraà giâ). Western scholars connect the word with the Greek &amp;lsquo;diametron,&amp;rsquo; aйaary:—Meru, Mandára, Vindhya, Gaudhamádana and others; sce Pár. P. V. 7,&#xA;कौतुक ०&#xA;SI. 2. The coremony preliminary to a marriage so called on account of the marriage&amp;ndash;thread (ŋw ) which forms the principal item in it. Cf. supra V. 66 and Rag. VIII. 1 (विवाहकौतुकम् ). Ohar, however says मङ्गलार्थं सुधारिकलेपादि यत्क्रियते तत्कौतुकमुच्यते । चैक - shows tho love which the citizens bore to their king.&#xA;(Sl.) 3. #rap-Properly one of the five trees of heaven but here used as a general term. महापथं महत् is compounded with पथ by the rule सन्महापरमोत्तमोत्कृष्टाः पूज्यमानैः । Páp. II. 1. 61. There is, however, a rule prohibiting the use of #ga with such words as पथिन्; wiZ. शंखे तैले तथा मासे वैद्ये ज्योतिषिके द्विजे । यात्रायां पथि निद्रायां महच्छब्दो न दीयते || But we find the word so compounded by great suthors. Cf. महात्राह्मण Sak. महात्रा-&#xA;S&amp;rsquo;ák. समूहजुष्टः पर्षद्वलान् महात्रराट् नैकटिकाश्रमान् । Bhatti So the rule seems to be of later growth. See Vámana on Páņ. VI. 2, 69. faige-Fine silk-cloth imported from China (which was famous for its silks from the earliest times) and much used for flags, not only for its beauty but also for its toughness. Cf.&#xA;( 104 )&#xA;चीनांशुकमिव केतोः प्रतिवातं नीयमानस्य । 8&amp;rsquo; &amp;amp;k. I. 31 उच्चित्रचीनांशुकgeareafdar &amp;amp;c. Mál. Mád. VI. 5. ratat-The comp. is&#xA;of the new. gender; cf. great.&#xA;पुत्रपौ-&#xA;S1, 4. -It is difficult to see what the poet means by this even though the comp. be taken as Malli. does. For according to the S&amp;rsquo;. P. Himalaya had two sons and two daughters only, viz. Maináka aud Krauñcha and Gauri and Gangá. Har हिमवतः पत्नी मैनाकं क्रौञ्चमेव च । गौरीगंगां च सुषुवे भवानाश्लेषपावनीम् ॥&#xA;S. P. Váy. Sum. XV. 52, 53. Some say-aresgegrandaaदादिरूपायाम् म्रुतांत्थिता - The direct mention of death is inauspicious and should have been avoided. उच्छुसितं-C/ सा कलपतेzzgigaíña S&amp;rsquo;ák. III.&#xA;}&#xA;S1. 6. मंत्र मु० - मित्रो देवतास्येति मैत्रः fr. मित्र + अणू ( अ ) by e a Pán. IV. 2. 24. According to Malli. this is the third muhurta (a period of 48 minutes) from sunrise, i. e. after 1 hour and 36 minutes after sunrise. According to another view this muhúrta is the period of the sun&amp;rsquo;s (apparently) passing through the lunar mansion Auurádhá (part of the zodiacal sigu scorpion) in the course of the day. The sun is the presiding deity of this constellation. Farho -Tho twelfth lunar mansion (one of the nakshatras mentioned as auspicious for the performance of ceremonies ). qrago-For women who have lost their husbauds or who are souless are thought to be unfit for taking part in such ceremonies.&#xA;A&#xA;Sl. 7. fazr-fastelsarą | white mustard which keeps off evil influences; of सरीषपः सिते तस्मिन् रक्षाघ्नो भूतनाशनः । Rabhasa. gaia grass is also held sacred by the Hindus and is worn by ladios along with flowers as auspicious (sce (so8 Vik. III. 12). offered to deities &amp;amp;c. fifa-fanifu may be explained as facqfa arf coveruing the navel, or as Malli. does. Some take faЯif to mean · musk &amp;rsquo; ( fañāt arì: produced from the navel of the musk deer); musk and silk-cloth, or a silk-cloth scented with musk. Chár. takes the comp. as fa f¤€ÎÑ¢ ga in which the silk-cloth worn round the navel was removed (as she was to be anointed); but as if dissatisfied with this way of taking it (for the spoiling of a silken cloth was no consideration in the caso of Himalaya) he also interprets it as Malli, doos. कौशेयं-कोश संभूतं by कौशाहू Pán. IV. 3. 42. (ít¶ à fær af Kás&amp;rsquo;iká). This shows&#xA;( 105 )&#xA;that in Panini&amp;rsquo;s days the art of making cloth from cocoons of silk-worms was known and cultivated,&#xA;उपात्तबाणम्This refers to the custom according to which when there was a marriage between a husband of an exalted rank or higher class and a woman of a lower rank, a Kshatriya girl had to catch hold of au arrow held by her hand as she had not the privilege of directly joining her hand with that of her husband of शरः क्षत्रियया ग्राह्यः प्रतोदो वैश्यकन्यया । वसनस्य दशा ग्राद्या शूद्रयवेद || Maun. III. 44. ( Seo also Yajñavalkya I 62 ) This passage is differently explained by different Commentators क्षत्रियया पाणिग्रहणस्थाने ब्राह्मणविवाहे ब्राह्मणहस्तपरिगृहीतकाण्डेकदेशी gg: 1 Kullúka. Medhâtithi nearly says the same and adds पाणिग्रहणस्थाने शरस्य विधानात् । Narayana, however, says क्षत्रियया धृतं शरं पाणिग्रहणमन्त्रेवरी गृह्णीयात् । Raghavananda says - दशरः पाणिना क्षत्रियया गृहीतो यस्तं पाणिस्थानीयं विमी गृह्णीयात्&amp;hellip; अन्यथा मन्त्रविरोधः । Following probably this statement the poet makes Párvati take an arrow in her hand as she was to marry Siva, vastly her superior in rank. अलंचकार - The grace of her person lent charm to her dress instead of the dress setting off her person. Cf. आमरणस्याभरणं प्रसाधनविधः प्रसाधनविशेषः । &amp;amp;c. Vik II असमग्रभूषणायास्तनुतर कौशयवासधारिण्याः । आलिप्तमङ्गमखिले तैलेन सुगन्धिना&#xA;तस्याः । Par. P.&#xA;Sl. 8 वीक्षाविधिo Perhaps the custom was provalent in Kâli.&amp;rsquo;s time. करेण - सुषुम्णाख्येन - Cha; by the ray called Sushumá (also called सुषुम्न ) - One of the seven principal rayof the sun enpplying heat to the moon. Cf सूर्यरश्मिः सुपुत्रो यस्तर्पितस्तेन चन्द्रमाः । कृष्णपक्षेमरेः शश्वत्पयते वै सुधामयः ॥ V. P. II. 2. 22. अथाप्यस्यैका रश्मिश्चन्द्रमसं पति दीप्यते &amp;hellip; । सुषुम्णः सूर्यरश्मिश्चन्द्रमा गन्धवं इत्यपि निगमो भवति । Nirakta II. 2. 2. संधुश्य - Chari. reads संधुक्षमाणा which is better. The quotation given by Malli. ( read, aftor क्षपयन्तिः दर्पणोदरनिहिता इव मन्दिरस्यान्तः ॥ ) is from Varáhamihira&amp;rsquo;s Br. Eam; cf. also पुपोष वृद्धिं हरिदश्वदीधितेरनु - प्रवेशादिव बाल चन्द्रमाः । Rag. III. 22.&#xA;€&#xA;(Sl.) 9. • कल्क - The lodhara-burk pounded with water. आश्यान - p. p. of ir with आ. कालेय-कालेयक is given in Amara as &amp;amp; synonym of दारुहरिद्रा; but that does not seem to be intended here; and again as a kind of fragrant yellow pigment-अथ जायकं । कालीयकं ( कालेयकं . 7 ) च ) which Malli, follows here. According to Haláyndha it micane, saffron &amp;lsquo;काश्मीरजं च विद्वद्भिः कालेयं जागुरुं स्मृतम् ; and this will also do here.&#xA;氤&#xA;( 106 )&#xA;Malli. himself, commenting on Sis&amp;rsquo;. XII. 14. ( कालीयकक्षोदविलेपनश्रियं दिशदिशामुल्ल सदंशुमदद्युति) understands it in this sense and quotes S&amp;rsquo; ús&amp;rsquo; vats in support of it; चतुष्क - चत्वारोवयवा अस्य ।&#xA;(Sl.)&#xA;(10.) विन्यस्त० &amp;amp;c. -Malli. soems to take this in the sense of a floor laid with &amp;amp;e. see trans. ; it may also be taken in the sense of-in which a large slab formed of settings of Vaiduryas was placed. Ohár reads oशिले च तस्मिन्भक्तिOrnamental arrangement. Chár. reads अविद्ध (unperforated ) मुक्ता०. अष्टापद - अष्टौ धातवः पदानि अस्य. The अ of अट is longthoned by अटनः संज्ञायाम् । Pán. VI. 3. 126, when the comp. formed is a name; but अष्टपुत्रः तोयाः - Chár. स्नप० also स्नापयां०. मणिपीठवर्तिनीं तां मङ्गलशंखेषु मन्द्रघेोषेषु । अम्भोभिरमरनयाः सखीजनो विहितमज्जनामकरोत् ॥ Pár. P.&#xA;SI. 11. उद्गमनीय - A bleached or white cloth. According to Amaru ( see com.) it refers to a pair of washod ( whitened ) garments. No stress is to be laid on युग. According to Kshirasvamin it means that which is soon ( यलक्ष्यं तदेव ); the upper garment is also seen as well as the one put undernoath; hence the term applies to both प्रत्युद्रम is the read - ing of Char. and in Chhandomañjari-fit for going forth to meet or welcoming the bridegroom निर्वृत्तपर्जन्य० -पर्जन्य fr. पृष् to shower + अन्य Unádi III. 103. पर्षति वृष्टिं ददातीतिः ष boing irregularly ( निपातनात् ) chauged to जू. प्रफुल्लुकाशाcorrespouds to—०नीयवस्रा / मङ्गल भज्जनविषदा कर्पूरक्षादपाण्डुरं क्षौमम् । साधत्त जलदधौता यौरिव शरदिन्दुचन्द्रिकाद्भेदम् ॥ Par. I.&#xA;(Sl.) 12. चतुष्टय - चत्वारोवयवा अस्य | परिगृह्य - See Malli.; or having taken her with them. कौतुक -कौतुकार्था ( see&#xA;(1.) 2) afą:.&#xA;S1. 14. त्याजित - p. p. of the cau of श्यज् here used as a root governing two accusatives. Some grammarians, Sudhákara and others. iuclnde roots liko त्यजू, मुच् &amp;amp;c. in the list of the roots on the authority of in Patanjali&amp;rsquo;s Kárikâनीवह्यो हरनेश्वापि गत्यर्थानां तथैव च । द्विकर्मकेषु महणं द्रष्टव्यमिति निश्वयः । of. Rag. स्याजितैः फलमुत्खात: &amp;amp;c. IV. 33, भरतस्तत्र गन्धर्वान्युधि निर्जित्य केवलम् । आतोद्यं ग्राहयामास समत्याजयदायुधम् ॥ XV. 88. Others do not adopt this view. Kaiyata on अकथितं च Pan. I. 4. 61 Bays गवा पयस्त्याजयतिः of. Bhatti सन्त्याजयांचकाराथ सीतां विंशतिबाहुना | उदार - Oharming. Cf. आगुल्फलम्बमस्याः कुन्तलमन्तर्निगूढ - मन्दारम् । संयम्य चतुरबन्धं सखीजनस्तिमितनेत्रमास चिरम् ॥ Pár. P.&#xA;( 107 )&#xA;Sl. 15 अगुरु-Fragrant also wood ale called राजाई. पत्रornamental paintings. विभक्त - diversified or variegated with. ० विभङ्ग . . ( Oha. ) गोरोचनायाः पत्रविभङ्गाः पत्रलता यत्र. सैकत - Sandy bank; fr. सिकता + अणू by सिकताशर्कराभ्यांच | Pah. V. 2. 104. ( सिकताः सन्त्यस्मिन्देश इति सैकती देशः ).&#xA;Sl. 10. लभ - Chár तद्यदलीनषट्पदम् Bhatti Mall. takes the Ins.&#xA;roads लीन; for the idea of. न पङ्कजं 11 19. प्रसिद्धै: - 900 V. 9. अलकै :उपलक्षणे: it may also be taken करणे; on account of Cha&amp;rsquo;r remarks - कमलशशिनी किल मुखस्योपमानभूतौ । अभिभवे तु प्रसाधनमेव हेतुः ।&#xA;Sl. 17. कषाय - An unguent or thick juice of . As it is astringent it made the check a little rough भेद - 7. interwixture with. परभाग-Lit. the chief or excellent portion ; &amp;amp; position of advantage; supreme cxcellence परलाभी गुणोत्कर्षः Hala&amp;rsquo;yndha and Abhi. Chin.&#xA;SI.&#xA;(18.) सुविभक्त - well-proportioned symmetrical विमृष्टpolished off. Cha&amp;rsquo;ri. reads faze. कामाय -of सूर्यापाये न खलु कमनं पुष्यति स्वामभिख्याम् | Meg. II. 20 वपुरभिनवमस्याः पुष्यति स्वां न शोभां Shak. I.&#xA;Yama is a period of&#xA;SI. 21. बियामा - तिस्रो यामा यस्याः. three hours. The night proper has three such periods; only the first half of the first and the second half of the last being left out, as they are almost like day, there being some light and the people being active as during the day; or त्रीन्यापयतीति that which dismisses the three, viz. धर्म, अर्थ and मोक्ष-the time boing specially suited to काम.&#xA;(Sl.) 24. स्तनोद - Sce I. 40. मनोरथ - viz to bestow her in. marriage on Siva. प्रथमं - s00 I. 50. Cf तस्या ललाटसीमनि चन्दनपङ्केन मेनया लिखितम् । आसीत्सितातपत्रं तिलकमनङ्गस्य दर्शितच्छायम् ॥ Pár. P.&#xA;(61.) 26. क्षीरोद -The milky ocean is selected on account of its whiteness. क्षौम This was of a white colour as the comparison to फेनपु० shows.&#xA;S1. 27. कुलप्रतिष्ठां - वंशयशस्करी Chár. क्रमेण - अनुज्येष्ठं according to seniority.&#xA;च&#xA;Sl. 29. ० प्रतीक्ष:&amp;ndash;An Upapada T : ण ( अ ) being added by fearai a Várt, ou Páṇ. III. 2, 1. Malli.&amp;rsquo;s statement कर्मण्यणू seems to be from oversight.&#xA;(61.) 30. तत्पूर्व ० - सदेव पूर्वमयं श्रेष्ठं वा and not प्रथमं as Siva was first married to Daksha&amp;rsquo;s daughter सती, or तत्पूर्वस्य पाणिग्रह-&#xA;( 108 )&#xA;णस्य similar to that of his first marriage, मातृभिः -The divine mothers attending on S&amp;rsquo;iva. They are seven&#xA;|&#xA;d कौमारी वैष्णवी तथा । माहेन्द्री चैव वाराही चामुण्डा सप्त मातरः ॥ or ब्राह्मी माहेश्वरी चैन्द्री वाराही वैष्णवी तथा । कौबेरीत्यपि कौमारी सप्तैवं मातरः स्मृताः ॥ ; or eight according to some ब्राह्मी कोमारी चैव चामुण्डा चार्चिकेत्यष्ट मातरः || According to others they are eighteen but they are not meant here; as if forms one of the list. Streaïfa:-31Ã¡ ¤guíââ Amara.; full of respect or worshipful. पुरशासन: - ( पुरस्य शासन: ) it is better to take this as &amp;amp; Gen. Tat. ; if we follow Malli, the agza (in most cases and not in a few) provided by ayat age will have to be resorted to to keep off अण.&#xA;Sl. 32. fæaro-Unguent of white Aguru. rf:-i, e. fra:—the beautiful head-ornament.&#xA;(Sl.) 35. fagza-p), p. p. faq with fa emitted, sent forth. चूडामणे :उभयप्राप्ती कर्माण इति षष्ठी - हरस्य tho gen. is कर्तरि -&#xA;S1. 37. af&amp;ndash;See III. 41.&#xA;-Kailása is the site&#xA;of Kubera&amp;rsquo;s capital and the favourite abode of S&amp;rsquo;iva. It is white and the bull is compared to it on account of his whiteness and large size; see Rag. II. 35.&#xA;Sl. 38. qua-A bed of lotuses of golden hue (as the deities were of golden complexion; see next sl.). stratieiयावापृथिव्योरन्तः ईश्यते इति; fr. ईश् + अ ( घञ् कर्मणि ); or अन्तः ऋक्षाणि stars अस्य; in this case the word is अन्तरिक्ष.&#xA;Sl. 39. -The fierce blood-thirsty cousort of S&amp;rsquo;iva in his character of the destroyer of the world. She is reprosented as of a black colour, with a hideous and terrible countenance, dripping with blood, encircled with snakes, and hung ronud with skulls and human heads &amp;amp;c. She killed the demon Rakta-bija. On account of her black colour and huge form she is compared to a line of dark clouds, the skulls resembling cranes बलाकिनी - बलाका अस्या विद्यन्ते. Tho rainy season is the period of the gestation of the cranes and they are represented as congregating in the sky at the first appearance of clouds. Cf. Malli. on गर्भाधानक्षण परिचयान्नूनमाबद्धमालाः सेविष्यन्ते नयनसुभगं खे भवन्तं बलाकाः | Meg. शतह्रदाशतं हृदा अचषि rays,&#xA;flashes HEAT:&#xA;(Sl.) 41. #gacita:-The Par. p. makos S&amp;rsquo;esha the umbrellabearer; cf. चन्द्राकविपि चामरे विधुनुतां छत्री भवाहीश्वर । V. 24. तहुकूल&#xA;-the white silken cloth of the umbrella which looked like the( 109 )&#xA;white current of the Ganges when falling from heaven, Mall. explains the Abl. by the optionality given by guíažde, Pa&amp;rsquo;n. II. 3. 34. Ilis remark arЯtæ &amp;amp;c. means -Nâtha&amp;rsquo;s statement = &amp;amp;c. is without authority from original grammar. Again if this optionality (of eeqp。 ) be accepted that of gy。 becomes rejected and the use of the Gon. in gi ¤¶¶ cannot be defended. Bo Natha&amp;rsquo;s statement must be dismissed as untenablo.&#xA;(Sl.) 42 मूर्ति - P. 2 of मूर्च्छ सहंसपाने - The cluuries waved resembled swans alighting on the banks.&#xA;SI. 43. श्रीवत्स ० -Lit. the favourite of Sri; a peculiar auspicious mark-according to some, a curl of hair-on the breast of Vishnu. According to the Mali, Bhár. Sán. P. it is the mark loft by the stroke of S&amp;rsquo;iva&amp;rsquo;s S&amp;rsquo;ula, and according to to the Bhag. P. of Briga&amp;rsquo;s foot. See our mole on the word, Rag. X. 10.&#xA;(Sl.) 44. ¢¥ &amp;amp;c.-See supra II. 4, 6; cf. Rag. X. 16. Here the poet states his own belief in the unity of the three gods. It is the same god, one and alone, regarded in the three aspects of creating, protecting and withdrawing the manifested universe. This clearly shows that Kali. was not a bigoted S&amp;rsquo;aiva. His S&amp;rsquo;aivism was like that of the poet Blaṛtrihari, not even so pronounced (see Vai. S&amp;rsquo;a. 85). The natural pro pensity of his mind led him to be a worshipper of Siva; that is all. See our note ou Vik. I. 1.&#xA;S1. 45. लोकपालाः -These are इन्द्रो वह्निः पितृपति ( यमः ) -नैर्ऋतो वरुणो मरुत् ( वायु: ) । कुबेर ईशः पतयः पूर्वादीनां दिशां क्रमात् ॥ Amara. gg-gỗ ( fr, q+3 Uņádi I. 24) many. gaiuga:, पुरु प्रचुरमाह्वानं यज्ञेष्वस्य पुरूणि हूतानि नामान्यस्य इति वा ।&#xA;(Sl.) 46. शतपत्र ० - शतपत्रं (a lotus ) योनिर्यस्य. The description here shows how an Indian imperial king received his guests and subordinates.&#xA;(Sl.) 47. जयाशी :जयस्याशीः; or जयेत्या०, तिङन्ते न मयूरव्यंसका दयश्वेति तत्पुरुषः । अध्वर्यवः - Adhvarya is a particular priest; अध्वर्यूद्रातृहोतारो यजुःसामग्विदः क्रमात् । ; but the word is used here in the general sense of a priest; fr. 3%81+1+3(§; Unadi I. 38); अध्वरस्याकारलोपश्वेत्युज्वलदत्तः ।&#xA;(Sl.) 48. विश्वावसुविश्वं वसु यस्य. The अ is lengthened by विश्वस्य वसुराटो Pán. VI. 3. 128. प्रायहर-chief; पकष्टमयं पात्रं the foremost point ; प्राप्रे हरति; हरतेरनुद्यमने अच् ( अ ); Pay III. 2. 9.&#xA;K. N 10&#xA;( 110 )&#xA;( Pan.&#xA;प्रवीणैः - प्रकृष्टा वीणा अस्य । यद्वा वीणया प्रगायति । सत्यापIII. 1. 2 ) इति णिजन्तात्पचाद्यच । versed in playing on the lute; skilful musicians. त्रिपुरावदान: - 50e Malli, the valorous or glorious deed in connection with Tripura-i. e, his destroying with an arrow the three cities of gold, silver and iron built in the sky. in the aidspace and on earth by Maya for the demons. त्रिपुर may also moan the domon ( त्रीणि पुराण्यस्य ) and अवदान his destruction). spafac-see supra H. 58.&#xA;SI. 49. व tay be taken with खेलगामी or उवाह. चामीकरचमीको स्वणांकरभेद भवस्रः तत्र भवः इति अण यदा चामी शोभां करोतीति चामीकरस्य किंकिण्यम यद्वा चामीकरस्य विकारा: चामीकराः । विकारार्थे अश | कचिदपवादविषयेपि उत्सर्गोभिनििवशते इति भाण्यात् | now see Mulli. azr-Sec I. 56.&#xA;(Sl.) 50. म. &amp;ndash;Char. 1akes this to refer to Siva. मुहतातल्यक्लप कर्मण्यधिकरणे चेति वक्तव्यात्पञ्चमी । दृष्टिपातैः - the glances darted irom the third eye ( हरतृतीयनयनपातः Char ) which had a golden brightness.&#xA;SI. 51.&#xA;घननील-धन 1 mloud; | dark like &amp;amp;c. ) or deop-dark.. स्ववाण:the path marked by the light of his arrowie the corial region sce Malli sermo tuke it to rofor to the arrow -hot 1y Siva at Brahma when running, with his pission inthiumed after his danghter ( स्वकन्यागमनोयतं ब्रह्माणमाहन्तुं निक्षित आद्रनक्षत्र पेण स्थितः शिवस्य बाण एव चिह्नं यस्य ). See supra IV. 41. C/ प्रजानाथं नाथ प्रसभमभिक स्वां दुहितरं गतं रोहितां रिमयिमृष्यस्य वपुषा । धनुष्पाणिर्यात दिवमपि सपत्राकृतमनुं वसन्तं तद्यापि त्यजति न मृगव्याधरभसः | Puspadanta&amp;rsquo;s Mahimua sl 22. The constellation मृगाशरम ( orion / is Brahma आर्द्रा the arrow.&#xA;।&#xA;(Sl.) 62 प्रतीतः ख्यति हृष्टे प्रतीतः Amare प्रतीतः सादरे ज्ञाते हृष्टप्रख्यातयोत्रिषु । Medini, प्रफुल्ल 1. p. of फुल्ल 1. P. to bloom or फल 1 1 to burst open ( फुल्ल or फुल्त in this sense ; फलित in other seuses ).&#xA;Sl.&#xA;S1. 58. अविधान also पिधान. भिन्नैक० - The simile vividly expresses the idea of the two pressing crowds mingling together. 56. This sl. occurs with necessary modifications in Rag. See VII, 5. Now the poet proceeds to describe the confusion of the ladies of the town hurrying to obtain a good view of S&amp;rsquo;iva and the procession. Such descriptions are common enough in Sanskrit; Of. S&amp;rsquo;is&amp;rsquo;. XIII. 30-48, Bud, Ch. III. 13-24, Vikraman. VI. 11-19.&#xA;(111)&#xA;1&#xA;सुन्दरीणाम-सुट उननि इतिः fr. + उन्+अर like शकन्धुः Bee Várt. on Pân, VI. 1. 94. Fem. gr. Cf de quai द्विषः पटहमणादविहितापहृतयः । अवधीरितान्यकरणीयसत्वरा प्रतिरथ्यमीयुरथ dträffa: ) # Sis&amp;rsquo;. XIII. 30.&#xA;(Sl.) 57-Slokas 57-62 are almost the same as iu Rag. VII. ( 6-11). आलोकमार्ग - आलोक्यतेऽनेन इत्या window of आलोक may meman light तस्य मार्गम् उद्वेष्टन उहतं बटनमस्य म उद्वेष्टनः । प्रादिभ्यो धातजस्य वाच्यो वाचोत्तरपदलोपः इति चीहि वान्तं माल्य येनः आदौं उ० पश्चाद्वान्तमान्यः । मालैव माल्यम् । चर्वणादिण्य | Virt où Pân. V. 1. 124; or gaga zfa nga ( 4 ) by Pay. III. 1. 124. ara-The use of the word is not objectionable here as it is used in a metaphorical sonse, riz. that of thrown down&amp;rsquo;; sec note on 744 VI. 37. aga here may mean a string by which it was tied up. arga-here adds emphasis:-noi&#xA;at all. Malli says eqde but not in good taste. For if the lady did not think of tying up her hair when making for the window it&#xA;was less likely that she should think of it when actually at the window where her attention would be more engrossed. gnq-This shows how great her absend-mindedness was. Châr, say: 591men az ala ezfaa va aniq set, but without propriety, as it does not bring out the ladies&amp;rsquo; absentmindedness so prominently Fuaj 5817. Famar, i a Nityasamása.&#xA;N1 38. अगानम -See Malli It dissolved as green the comp. will be ggpą. Malli quotes Vámana-the meaning ithe compounds gears and 30go are obtained by taking yo ( styei ) and goft ( gear ) as distinct and as identical ro÷pec tively. In the present case the nm, sua resides in the foot which is the ŋor. The poet here speaks of them both as identical disregarding the distinction between the whole grg and its forepart to which alone the 32 properly belongs. See our note on this at Rag VII 7 गवामक्षीव गवाक्षः । The word signifies a window by Kudhi ( usage) Nee notes on 62. further on. Cf. with this S&amp;rsquo;is&amp;rsquo;. XIII. 33.&#xA;SL 59. This implies extreme hurry; see Malli., ef. Nimittaniding वामभागस्तु नारीणां भ्रष्टः पुंसां तु दक्षिणः । दाने देवादिTAZİ JERETÓngan The lady was in such a hurry that when she heard that the procession was advancing she besmeared hor right eye and then at once ran to the window.&#xA;SI. 60.&#xA;जाला०-जालान्तरे-न्तरेण वा प्रेषिता दृष्टिर्यया । नाभिप्र०-The word fax indicates depth of the navel, which is supposed&#xA;( 112 )&#xA;to be a mark of beauty. See supra I. 38; cf. Rag. VI. 52. ( आवर्तमनोज्ञनाभिः ) ( ) हरिवीक्षणाक्षणिक चक्षुषान्यया करपल्लवेन गलदम्बरं&#xA;S&amp;rsquo;is&amp;rsquo;. XIII, 44.&#xA;P. A to&#xA;Sl. 61. अर्धा - A comp. सुप्सुपा दुर्निमित-fr. measure, to establish (The root is rarely used in classical literature ); ill-measured, ill-placed. The woman was stringing her girdle with pearls fastening one oud of the string to her big-toe. But when she heard of the approach of the procession she ran to the window. forgetting in her hurry to secure the part of the waist-hand that was strung and so all the pearls dropped down, the string only being left hanging by her great-toe.&#xA;०-&#xA;Sl. 62. आसवगन्धगभैःThe word गर्भ takes परनिपात by Vart. गवादिभ्यः परा सप्तमी. Drinking wine sooms to have been a fashionable vice with the men and women of the higher societies in ancient India, if it is not merely a poetical fiction; cf. S&amp;rsquo;is&amp;rsquo;. X. 33 quoted by Malli. while commenting on IV. 12. supra; cf. also ककुद्मिकन्यावस्त्रान्तर्वासलब्धाधिवासया । मुखामोदं मंदिरया कृतानुव्याधमुद्रमन ॥ Sis&amp;rsquo;. II. 20. सान्द्र० This shows that the women remained stationary and so their faces looked like lotuses. भ्रमरेः -भ्रमन् रोतीति । भ्रमतीति वा भ्रमरः । fr. भ्रम् +अर (3⁄4fdíng-sfa za Ugádi III. 132). It is customary with poets to describe lotuses with bees hovering about them, Tag:—it means a ray of light; f something like an eye. a hole, sa becomes sig at the end of a compound when it does not mean - au eye&amp;quot;, by 3⁄4¢uzdara | Pág. V. 4. 76. Ilence mag means a hole for admitting light and so a window by Ru&amp;rsquo;dhi or usage. Though the word ought to be new. (80 it is givon ín Kás ́ikâ ) it is mas, by custom. ( ývá šeľa). Mano-&#xA;rama and Tatv. Bod.&#xA;(Sl.) 68. इन्दुमौलिः &amp;ndash;इन्दुमैलौ यस्य Vyad Bah.; मौलि takes परनिपात by गड़वादिभ्यः &amp;amp; see last sl. राजपथं - राज्ञः पन्थाः; or पथ राजा the chief road; here पथिन् takes परनिपात by राजदन्तादिषु परम् ।&#xA;Pân, II. 2. 31.&#xA;(Sl.) 64. fefu: qr-is a Sauskṛit idiom for to look intently at&amp;rsquo;, see Rag. II. 19,73. :—ie, by their senses. fqq10-&#xA;विषया अन्ये विषयाः वि० राणि । विषिण्वन्ति निबध्नन्ति इन्द्रियाणि इति विषया: those which attract the senses; hence the objects of sonses. ‘aga¤775zala zoqjza ♬ ergfugazíta « farafa Ohár. The women were looking at S&amp;rsquo;iva so intently that the power of perception of&#xA;( 113 )&#xA;Notice&#xA;the other senses seemed to be quite paralysed, ears caught no sound, the skin felt no touch &amp;amp;c. Cf. Rag. VII, 12. the roading ताः शङ्करं in this connection.&#xA;(Sl.) 65. अपर्णया - For the name soe supra V. 28. पलवापेलवं विरलं तनु Amara; hence dolicate, tender.&#xA;SI.&#xA;(61.) 66. परस्परेण - may also be taken with स्पृ० इन्दुमत्याः शांभाऽजेन स्पृहणीयस्याजस्य शोभा चेन्दुमत्या इत्यर्थः । शोभयतीति शोभा । Hemádri. द्वन्द्वंद्वौ द्वौ इति । हिशब्दस्य द्विर्वचनं पूर्वपदस्याम्भावः अलं चोत्तरपदस्य | by द्वन्द्वं रहस्यमर्यादावचन &amp;amp;c. Pán VIII. 1. 15. Cf. Rag. VII. 14, and निशा शशाङ्कं शिवया गिरीशं श्रिया हरिं योजयतः प्रतीतः । विधेरपि स्वारसिकः प्रयासः परस्परं योग्यसमागमाय ॥.&#xA;g).&#xA;·&#xA;Sl. 67. व्रीडात्-बीड fr. बीड 4. I to be ashamed + अ (घ ) with a by Pan. III. 3. 103. ( &amp;lsquo;गुरोश्च&amp;rsquo; हल: ) बीडा; of बीडमावहति मे स संपति Rag. XI. 73. व्रीडादिवाभ्यासगत विलिये | Sis&amp;rsquo;. III. 40.&#xA;(69.) त्रिनेत्र - Malli, hore avoids the णख by rejecting its संज्ञात्व on the authority of Pan. VIII. 4. 30. केयूर०लाजमुष्टिं -It was customary for ladies, young and old, to shower handfuls of lájas (rice grains parched without being husked which swell considerably and lose the husk in the process of parching) on a distiguished person, &amp;amp;c. as an auspicious sign ( माङ्गलिकत्वात् ). See Rag. II. 10. पदे पदे विवाहानल इव कुसुममिश्रलांजाञ्जलिभिरवकीर्यमाणश्चन्द्रापीड: &amp;amp;c. Kad. p. 140. The word लाज is was, and used in the plural; दाराक्षतलाजातूनां बहुत्वं च । इति लिङ्गानुशासन सूत्रम् । चूर्णीकृतं - पुरन्धि जन सम्बन्धातिशयोक्तिः । Mulli. The Iajns were powdered rather as they came in contact with the Leyuras worn by the large assemblage of men. The keyuras are worn by men; cf. Raghu. VI. 68, Bhar, 1, Nit. 19. Cf. Rag. VII. 16.&#xA;Sl. 70. अच्युत - नास्ति च्युतं स्वपदात्स्खलनमस्य । उक्षन् a bull; fr. उक्ष से चने भ्वादि: + अन् (कनि by श्वन्नुक्षन् &amp;amp;c. Unadi I. 182) कक्ष्याa room or hall; also कक्षा&#xA;•&#xA;81, 72 विष्टर – A seat; the स् is changed to aftor वि whon the meaning is a tree or a seat; garaadiffer: 1 Páṇ. VIII. 3. 03, but वाक्यस्य विस्तरः यथावत् - यथार्हम् । तदर्हमिति वतिः । ८ / ततो यथावद्विहिताध्वराय । Rag. V. 19. अध्यापिपगाधिसुतो यथावत् । Bhatti. II. 21. गव्यं गोरिदम् । by गोपयसेोर्यत् । Pan. IV. 3. 160; clarified&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
