<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Pauranic testimony and some time lines in Hindu tradition</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-11_the-pauranic-testimony-and-some-time-lines-in-hindu-tradition/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-11_the-pauranic-testimony-and-some-time-lines-in-hindu-tradition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/06/11/the-pauranic-testimony-and-some-time-lines-in-hindu-tradition/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I believe that despite all the noise on the topics the purANas are at&#xA;this point more enlightening on certain points than all the archaeology&#xA;of the Indian subcontinent. In fact it appears important that the future&#xA;archaeological studies in India, if they occur at all, must keep in the&#xA;mind the Pauranic timelines for poorly known Hindu dynasties. At the&#xA;outset I must make it clear that some well-known dates contested&#xA;recently by Hindu historical revisionists are indeed correct. Where the&#xA;real revision of Hindu dates is required is of an earlier era. The&#xA;acceptable dates that I find emerging from the purANas are:&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Western: Alexander of Macedon, the yavana invader of India= 356-323 BCE.&#xA;This date is important for it is indeed a sheet anchor intersection&#xA;between the neo-yavana world and the Hindu world.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Hindu: mahAvIra the founder of the jaina mata467 BCE&lt;br&gt;&#xA;That is his entire life can be definitely mapped between this period.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;gautama buddha452 BCE&lt;br&gt;&#xA;chandragupta mauraya 288 BCE&lt;br&gt;&#xA;The nandas of magadha were definitely a major imperial power in eastern&#xA;India at the time of the invasion of Alexander of Macedon. We can be&#xA;sure that they came to power at least by 334 BCE and were ousted by&#xA;chandragupta and kautilya at least by 312 BC.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mid-night thoughts on Pauranic testimony</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-10_mid-night-thoughts-on-pauranic-testimony/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-10_mid-night-thoughts-on-pauranic-testimony/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/06/10/mid-night-thoughts-on-pauranic-testimony/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“Hindus have no historical sense”; “India is a cul de sac”; “upaniShads&#xA;and the buddha were contemporaneous and had Greek influence”. I heard&#xA;all this gibberish and more from my school textbooks and leftist&#xA;colleagues. I had long back silently noticed the precision with which&#xA;Hindus recorded dates on their stone and copper plate inscriptions, be&#xA;it Sanskrit or a regional dialect. This immediately brought home to me&#xA;in a flash that the white scholars and their fellow-travellers were&#xA;looking for Hindu historicity in the wrong places. In fact, the texts&#xA;which were believed to contain historical records were dismissed as&#xA;being full of balony by the white scholars and their apers. I always had&#xA;a certain respect for the purANa-s and noticed that their genealogical&#xA;testimonies were indeed surviving, even if corrupt fragments of hoary&#xA;Hindu history, that actually recorded rulers of jamdbudvIpa. Obviously&#xA;there were many hoary kShatriya-s who were famous, like mandhAtA,&#xA;trasadasyu, kArtavIrya, bhagIratha, bharata, raghu, rAmachandra,&#xA;hiraNyanAbha, yuddhiShThira, kR^iShNa etc. But then there were also many&#xA;who were only names– yet the purANas faithfully preserved them and&#xA;despite the corruptions in texts had a largely consistent flow. Why&#xA;should these be preserved — especially in certain cases like the&#xA;bArhadrathas with some numerical figures with each king even if his only&#xA;mention was in these dynastic lists. It immediately struck me that the&#xA;paurANic testimony is real hindu history of a hoary time. In course of&#xA;my deep investigations of these genealogies I noticed that two white&#xA;scholars had independently appreciated the importance of the purANas as&#xA;historical tradition and had paid most careful attention to their&#xA;genealogies- Pargiter and Morton Smith. Still they had their biases- and&#xA;got some key sheet anchors wrong. But much of their work is still useful&#xA;and confirmed by my own studies. Ishwa Mishra is an internet raconteur&#xA;who has also invested a lot of effort on this matter but many of his&#xA;speculative forays are seriously misplaced despite the useful mass of&#xA;information he collects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The temple of irAvAn</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-08_the-temple-of-iravan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-08_the-temple-of-iravan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/06/08/the-temple-of-iravan/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In addition to the temples of draupadi ammAL there are a cluster of&#xA;temples of irAvAn close to the point the where my paternal ancestor&#xA;first immigrated to the Dravida country. Our clanswoman had obtained a&#xA;detailed account of the itihAsa of irAvAn from one of the most learned&#xA;smArta bhAratiyAr-s of that locality whose clan was associated with that&#xA;of our ancestors for a while. Of course the smArta narrative differs&#xA;quite drastically from the narratives of the tevar and other tamil&#xA;pAratiyAr-s. It goes thus:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>draupadi ammAL and chunItan</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-22_draupadi-ammal-and-chunitan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 May 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-22_draupadi-ammal-and-chunitan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2006/05/22/draupadi-ammal-and-chunitan/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A sub-set of the smarta brahmins of Gingee, Melaccheri Kadu and parts of&#xA;the modern Telugu country upwards of Kalahasti, usually belonging to the&#xA;great sect of bR^ihatcharaNaM or rarely the vaDamas (northerners), are&#xA;called pAratiyAr-s. There are other pAratiyAr-s belonging the middle&#xA;caste vELALar-s. Both of them are associated with the draupadi ammAL&#xA;temples of the region, whose many patrons are vanniyar-s. The vanniyar-s&#xA;are described by some as shUdra or avarNa, but their and internal&#xA;beliefs point to the possibility that they were actually vahni-kula&#xA;rAjaputra-s. Both the smArta and vELALar pAratiyArs are experts in the&#xA;narration of the mahAbhArataM or the makApArataM as they respectively&#xA;call it. Their versions are obviously different. The vELALar version, is&#xA;very popular with the vanniyars and they enact it in kuttu-s or&#xA;Dravidian dance-dramas, though the smArta version too is enacted by&#xA;these actors. The vELALar form is ahistoric, anachronistic and full of&#xA;local Dravidian deities. While the smArtas too incorporate some of these&#xA;their narrative of the draupadi ammAL kathai has an interesting&#xA;consistency with the paurANIc narratives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The jaina view</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-24_the-jaina-view/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-24_the-jaina-view/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;js_include&#34; url=&#34;https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/AgamaH/AryaH/jainaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-24_the-jaina-view.md&#34;  newLevelForH1=&#34;5&#34; includeTitle=&#34;false&#34;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition locus</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/composition-locus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/composition-locus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/blog_supplement/status/1480776566875508736&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;rAmAyaNa mentions janapada significantly more frequently (per hemistich omitting uvAcha and UchuH lines) than mahAbhArata or harivaMsha. Mbh mentions rAShTra significantly more than R&amp;amp;H. nagara is nearly identical in R&amp;amp;H but marginally less in bhArata. Could this be reflection of the polities of the text redactors. The rAmAyaNa&amp;rsquo;s janapada dominance might suggest an early eastern locus, while the rAShTra dominance in mahAbharata old kuru-pA~Nchala core where rAShTra was an important word. harivaMsha&amp;rsquo;s state might also reflect the later time&amp;amp; sAtvatta locus.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>itihAsa contrast</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/itihAsa-contrast/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/itihAsa-contrast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;rule-based-warfare&#34;&gt;Rule-based warfare&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a curious inversion where the Mahābhārata in a setting of declining righteousness has stylized, set-piece, rule-bound(even if in the breach) warfare, while the Rāmāyaṇa in a setting of exacting righteousness has mostly melee warfare(with night-time arson too!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My interpretation of that was that the former (rAmAyaNa) was modeled on the invasion of non-Arya domain, wherein victory was the bottom-line. The latter (mahAbhArata) was a fight between related Arya-s for shravas through display of kShatradharma. Persisted in rAjpUt-s.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>mahiSha-s</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/mahiSha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/mahiSha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Image of nIlalohita rudra holding the corpse of the buffalo-demon hAlAhala from ahichChatra. The kShetra of the rudra is however the holy kurukShetra. There are 3 buffalo demons in H tradition:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The oldest is mahiSha slain by skanda;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;mahiSha slain by kumArI vindhyavAsinI&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;hAlAhala slain by nIlalohita rudra.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Briefly, the goddess who slays mahiSha in the archaic skandapurANa is vindhyavAsinI-kumarI-kaushikI; In the mArkaNDeyapurANa it is durgA-mahAlakshmI. A more elaborate account of this development would need a lot more space.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Syamantaka maNi origin</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/syamantaka-maNi-origin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam/meta/MT_lekhAH/syamantaka-maNi-origin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The opening of the syamantaka episode in the oldest surviving harivaMsha manuscripts accepted as &amp;ldquo;critical&amp;rdquo; in the Pune edition. Note, that unlike the popular narrative, the maNi was obtained from the ocean &amp;amp; not the sun.+++(5)+++ In this regard it might be seen as something close to the atharvavedic idea of the mother-of-pearl or pearl maNi.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How does one etymologize syamantaka? I &lt;em&gt;conjecture&lt;/em&gt; that it is related to syamana/syam[iI]k[aA] whose meanings themselves are bit murky but in reliable context could relate to the sea or a small invertebrate. Thus, we see syamantaka as being a potential name for something of molluscan origin (pearl) though we cannot rule out a coral.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
